Elisha Franklin Paxton Papers WLU.Coll.0273
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Elisha Franklin Paxton Papers
Inclusive 1845-1897
Bulk 1854-1863
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Paxton, Elisha Franklin
Paxton, Elizabeth White
Paxton, Matthew White, Jr.
Paxton, Robert Owen, Dr.
WLU.Coll.0273
.5 Linear Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Matthew White, Jr. & Robert O. Paxton.
Biographical / Historical
Elisha F. Paxton, a 1843 alumnus of Washington College was a member of a prominent pioneering family in Lexington, Virginia, members of whom are still prominent citizens.
Scope and Contents
The Elisha Franklin Paxton Papers are comprised primarily of the personal correspondences, business and military papers of Elisha F. Paxton between 1845 and 1863. The core of the personal letters are written from Paxton to his wife Elizabeth White Paxton during their courtship in the 1850s and during the American Civil War, 1861-1863, while he served as an officer in the Confederate States Army's 27th Virginia Infantry, a member of the staff of General Stonewall Jackson, and general in command of the Stonewall Brigade of the Army of Northern Virginia. Paxton was born in Rockbridge County, Virginia in 1828. He attended Washington College (Va.) and Yale University - both for two years. After graduating from Yale, he moved on to law school at the University of Virginia graduating in 1849. Paxton lived and practiced law primarily in Lexington, Va., but for a period in Logan County, Ohio. He had business interests in farming and real estate and was for a period the president of the Bank of Rockbridge in Lexington, Va. Paxton was an officer in the Rockbridge Rifles, a Rockbridge County (Va.) militia company formed in the wake of John Brown's Raid on Harper's Ferry, Va., in 1859. Paxton was a strong proponent of secession and when Virginia voted to exit the Union in the spring of 1861, Paxton marched to war as an officer with the Rockbridge Rifles company. The company became attached to the 27th Virginia Infantry, later a part of Stonewall Jackson's Brigade. Paxton, ascended the ranks ultimately achieving full command of the Stonewall Brigade as a brigadier general. He was killed on May 3, 1863 during the Battle of Chancellorsville (Va.). There are numerous items in this collection pertaining to his death including obituaries, recollections and reflections of his life and character. Other letter writers include his brother James Gallatin Paxton, Matthew White, Samuel F. Jordan, James G. Hamilton, William A. Glasgow, and William McCorkle, each from or connected to Rockbridge County. Other highlights of the collection include various reports written by Paxton as a member of Lexington's Franklin Society and Library Company which shed light on his perspectives on topics such as Secession. There is also a printed broadside for the sale of land at Rockbridge Baths, Virginia, in 1860.
Correspondence; Debates and debating -- Societies, etc.; Chancellorsville, Battle of (Virginia: 1863); Broadsides; Paxton, Matthew White, Jr.; Paxton, Robert Owen, Dr.; Paxton, James Gardiner; Confederate States of America. Army. Stonewall Brigade; Bank of Rockbridge (Lexington, Va.); Franklin Society and Library Company of Lexington (Lexington, Va.); Confederate States of America. Army. Rockbridge Rifles; Confederate States of America. Army, Virginia Infantry Units, 27th; Rockbridge Baths (Rockbridge County, Va.); Ohio--Logan County; Hamilton, James Gilbreath, 1817-1893; Jordan, Samuel Francis, 1805-1872; McCorkle, William; Graham, William A. (William Alexander)
- Elisha Paxton Correspondences, 1845-1860; Paxton, Elisha Franklin; White, Matthew; White, William; Hensley, William H.; 25 Item (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Paxton was in Bellefontaine, Ohio at this time and most of the correspondences are related to business.
  Ohio -- Bellefontaine
- Miscellaneous, 1808-1861; Bank of Baltimore; 10 Item (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This file consists of warrants, a circuit court summons, letters from the Bank of Baltimore, and a note for Jas. G. Paxton, endorsed by Elisha Paxton to E. F. Paxton.
  Warrants (Law); Paxton, James Gardiner
- Receipts, 1850-1860; Paxton, James Gardiner; Conevy, J. B.; Echols, E.; Samuel Waterbury, Cabinet and Upholstery Warehouse; McCorkle, William; Hamilton, James G.; McChesney, Frances, Mrs.; 19 Item (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Warehouse receipts
- Wartime Papers, 1862-1863; Kelly, Mary A.; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Paxton, James Gardiner; 18 Item (Box 1, Folder 5)
  This file consists of Elizabeth Paxton's obituary and many articles about the death of General Paxton. It also includes sympathy notes to Mrs. Paxton at the time of his death. There is notification of Paxton's death by d R. E. Lee.
  Obituaries; Correspondence; Paxton, Elisha Franklin; Paxton, Elizabeth White; Letcher, John
- Envelopes of Letters from Paxton to Elizabeth, 1861-1863; Paxton, Elisha Franklin; 12 Item (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Paxton, Elizabeth White
- Wartime Correspondence with Elizabeth, 1861; Paxton, Elisha Franklin; 17 Item (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Correspondence; Paxton, Elizabeth White
- Wartime Correspondence with Elizabeth, 1862; Paxton, Elisha Franklin; 12 Item (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Correspondence; Civil war; Paxton, Elizabeth White
- Wartime Correspondence with Elizabeth, 1863; Paxton, Elisha Franklin; Paxton, Elizabeth White; 12 Item (Box 1, Folder 9)
  This file also includes a letter written by Elizabeth to Elisha.
- Love Letters from E.F. Paxton to Elizabeth Hannah White, 1853-1854; Paxton, Elisha Franklin; Paxton, Elizabeth White; 8 Item (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Elisha and Elizabeth were married later in 1854. One of the letters is written by Elizabeth to Elisha.
  Correspondence
- Letters from Elisha to Elizabeth Written While on a Business Trip to Ohio, 1857; Paxton, Elisha Franklin; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letter from Elisha to Elizabeth from New York City, 1860-06-27; Paxton, Elisha Franklin; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Elisha went to New York to see a doctor about eye problems.
  Correspondence; New York (State) -- New York; Paxton, Elizabeth White
- Envelopes from Correspondences, Paxton, Elisha Franklin; Paxton, Elizabeth White; 20 Item (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Envelopes (Stationery)
- Family Correspondences, 1857-1873; Paxton, William Hays; Junkin, W. F.; White, Matthew Xavier; 4 Item (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Letter to J.G. Paxton, son of E.F. Paxton, from W. F. Junkin of Montclair, N.J., dated Feb. 22, 1873, acknowledging sympathy.Letter from W.H. Paxton of New Orleans to his brother, E.F. Paxton, dated May 7, 1857. It mentions receipt of W.H. Paxton's daughter's legacy of $300 from the daughter's grandmother, Margaret McNutt Paxton.Note to Mrs. E.F. Paxton from W.F. Junkin sent from Camp Paxton May 1863 saying he would like to buy one o General Paxton's horses.Letter from Matthew White, brother of Elizabeth, to his parents from Camp Cooper, dated Dec. 23, no year given.
  Correspondence; Paxton, John Gallatin
- Debate Papers, Paxton, Elisha Franklin; 6 Item (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Debates and debating; Manuscripts
- Endorsement of Judge John W. Brockenbrough for Court of Appeals, 1852; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Broadsides; Brockenbrough, John
- Military Papers, 1861-1863; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 16)
  A charge and specification preferred by Brig. Gen. E.F. Paxton against Brig. Gen. W.B. Talliaferro, PACS, at Camp Winder, Jan. 7, 1862.Copy of battlefield map dated March 20, 1863, sent to Brig. Gen. E.F. Paxton, cmdr. 1st BrigadeA $1000 Confederate States Cotton Coupon Loan, 1863
  Paxton, Elisha Franklin
- Miscellaneous, Paxton, Elisha Franklin; 5 Item (Box 1, Folder 17)
  This file includes an obituary of Mrs. Samuel B. Walker, a card from E.F. Paxton to Elizabeth, a note to E.F. Paxton from Annie R. Paine, and a card reading 'J. Gallatin Paxton, Lexington, Virginia.'
  Walker, Katherine Lee Hopkins; Paxton, John Gallatin
- Two Letters Concerning the Death of Elisha Paxton, 1883-1897; Paxton, Matthew W.; Barton, Randolph; 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Hotchkiss, Jedediah